<tool id="somatic_sniper" name="Somatic Sniper" version="1.0beta">
   <command>/bin/bash -v "$script"</command>
	<inputs>
		<param name="bam1" type="data" format="bam" label="Sample 1 BAM" help="As an example normal BAM"/>
		<param name="bam2" type="data" format="bam" label="Sample 2 BAM" help="As an example - cancer BAM" />
		
    <param name="refGenome" type="select" label="Reference genome">
                        <options from_data_table="gatk_picard_indexes">
                                <filter type="sort_by" column="2" />
                                <validator type="no_options" message="No genomes are available for GATK" />
                        </options>
     </param>
      <param name="minQuality" type="integer" label="Minimal quality of reads" value="1" 
            help="ﬁltering reads with mapping quality less than"/>
      <param name="minSomQual" type="integer" label="Minimal somatic quality" value="15" 
            help="ﬁltering somatic snv output with somatic quality less than"/>
     <param name="disable_priors" type="boolean" label="Disable priors" truevalue="-p" falsevalue="" checked="False" 
            help="disable priors in the somatic calculation. Increases sensitivity for solid tumors."/>
     <conditional name="use_prior">
                        <param name="condValue" type="select" label="Use prior probabilities" 
                              help="Use prior probabilities accounting for the somatic mutation rate">
                                <option value="Yes">Yes</option>
                                <option value="No">No</option>
                        </param>
                        <when value="Yes">
                           <param name="prior_probability" type="float" value="0.01" label="prior probability" 
                                help="-s   prior probability of a somatic mutation" />
                        </when>
                        <when value="No" />
      </conditional>
      <param name="theta" type="float" value="0.85" label="theta in maq consensus calling model"
              help="FLOAT theta in maq consensus calling model (for -c/-g)" />
      <param name="haplotypes" type="integer" label="number of haplotypes" value="2" 
            help="number of haplotypes in the sample (for -c/-g)"/>
      <param name="prior_diff" type="float" value="0.001" label="prior of a diﬀerence between two haplotypes"
              help="prior of a diﬀerence between two haplotypes (for -c/-g) [0.001000]" />
	 <param name="out_type" type="select" label="Output Format" 
                              help="Select output format">
                                <option value="classic">Classic</option>
                                <option value="vcf">VCF</option>
                        </param>


	</inputs>
	<outputs>
		<data format="txt" name="log" label="Execution Log" />
		<data format="txt" name="results" label="Output in Classic" >
                   <filter>out_type == 'classic'</filter>
                </data>
		<data format="vcf" name="resultsVCF" label="Output in VCF" >
                   <filter>out_type == 'vcf'</filter>
                </data>
	</outputs>
<configfiles>
    <configfile name="script">#!/bin/bash -v
  cd `dirname $log`
err="`dirname $log`/err.pipe"
echo \$err

mkfifo "\$err"
trap 'rm "\$err"' EXIT
tee $log &lt; "\$err" &gt;&amp;2 &amp;

bam-somaticsniper -q $minQuality -Q $minSomQual $disable_priors \
#if str( $use_prior.condValue ) == "Yes"
  -J -s $prior_probability \
#end if 
-T $theta -N $haplotypes -r $prior_diff -F "$out_type" -f "${ refGenome.fields.path }"  \
$bam2 \
$bam1 \
output.tmp \
  2&gt;"\$err"


#if str ( $out_type ) == "classic" :
mv output.tmp $results
#end if

#if str ( $out_type ) == "vcf" :
mv output.tmp $resultsVCF
#end if

  </configfile>
  </configfiles>
<help>The purpose of this program is to identify single nucleotide positions that are diﬀerent between tumor and normal (or, in theory, any two bam ﬁles). It takes a tumor bam and a normal bam and compares the two to determine the diﬀerences. It outputs a ﬁle in a format very similar to Samtools consensus format. It uses the genotype likelihood model of MAQ (as implemented in Samtools) and then calculates the probability that the tumor and normal genotypes are diﬀerent. This probability is reported as a somatic score. The somatic score is the Phred-scaled probability (between 0 to 255) that the Tumor and Normal genotypes are not diﬀerent where 0 means there is no probability that the genotypes are diﬀerent and 255 means there is a probability of 1 − 10255∕−10 that the genotypes are diﬀerent between tumor and normal. This is consistent with how the SAM format reports such probabilities.
There are two modes, the joint genotyping mode (-J) takes into account the fact that the tumor and normal samples are not entirely independent and also takes into account the prior probability of a somatic mutation. This probability can be scaled to control the sensitivity of the algorithm. An accurate value for this prior would be 0.000001, but this may result in a severe lack of sensitivity at lower depths. A less realistic prior probability will generate more sensitive results at the expense of an increase in the number of false positives. To get a similar sensitivity to the default mode, we recommend using a prior of 0.01. The default mode treats the two samples as if they came from two diﬀerent individuals. This mode uses a less accurate mathematical model, but yields good results, especially if the normal may contain some tumor cells or the tumor is quite impure.

Notes on running SomaticSniper
Minimally, you must provide the program the reference fasta the bams were aligned against (passed with the -f option), a tumor bam, a normal bam, and the ﬁlename of the resulting output ﬁle. We recommend ﬁltering out reads with a mapping quality of 0 (i.e. use -q 1) as they are typically randomly placed in the genome. We have also found that few variants with a somatic score less than 15 validate, but you may decrease the minimum score or increase it to a higher threshold (eg -Q 40). To obtain high conﬁdence sites, we recommend also thresholding the minimum average mapping quality for the variant base to 40 for reads aligned with BWA or 70 for reads aligned with MAQ. We have not tested other aligners at this time. Disabling priors is not recommended, but may increase sensitivity at the cost of a decrease in speciﬁcity.

Each line contains the following tab-separated values:
Chromosome
Position
Reference base
IUB genotype of tumor
IUB genotype of normal
Somatic Score
Tumor Consensus quality
Tumor variant allele quality
Tumor mean mapping quality
Normal Consensus quality
Normal variant allele quality
Normal mean mapping quality
Depth in tumor (# of reads crossing the position)
Depth in normal (# of reads crossing the position)
Mean base quality of reads supporting reference in tumor
Mean mapping quality of reads supporting reference in tumor
Depth of reads supporting reference in tumor
Mean base quality of reads supporting variant(s) in tumor
Mean mapping quality of reads supporting variant(s) in tumor
Depth of reads supporting variant(s) in tumor
Mean base quality of reads supporting reference in normal
Mean mapping quality of reads supporting reference in normal
Depth of reads supporting reference in normal
Mean base quality of reads supporting variant(s) in normal
Mean mapping quality of reads supporting variant(s) in normal
Depth of reads supporting variant(s) in normal


VCF

VCF output from SomaticSniper conforms to version 4.1 of the VCF speciﬁcation. Hence, each non-header output line contains the following ﬁelds:

Chromosome
Position
ID (unused)
Reference base
Alternate bases (comma separated)
Quality (unused)
Filters (unused)
INFO (unused)
FORMAT speciﬁcation for each sample
NORMAL sample data
TUMOR sample data
The following FORMAT ﬁelds will be populated for each of NORMAL and TUMOR.

ID	Number	Type	
Description
GT	 1	 String	
Genotype
IGT	 1	 String	
Genotype when called independently (only ﬁlled if called in joint prior mode)
DP	 1	 Integer	
Total read depth
DP4	 4	 Integer	
# high-quality ref-forward bases, ref-reverse, alt-forward and alt-reverse bases
BCOUNT	 4	 Integer	
Occurrence count for each base at this site (A,C,G,T)
GQ	 1	 Integer	
Genotype quality
JGQ	 1	 Integer	
Joint genotype quality (only ﬁlled if called in joint prior mode)
VAQ	 1	 Integer	
Variant quality
BQ	 .	 Integer	
Average base quality
MQ	 .	 Integer	
Average mapping quality
SS	 1	 Integer	
Variant status relative to non-adjacent normal: 0=wildtype, 1=germline, 2=somatic, 3=LOH, 4=unknown
SSC	 1	 Integer	
Somatic Score
Documentation on Somatic Sniper available here: http://gmt.genome.wustl.edu/somatic-sniper/1.0.0/documentation.html
This program developed by: David E. Larson, Travis E. Abbott and Christopher C. Harris October 26, 2011
</help>
</tool>
